The Agecroft Collection
The Agecroft Collection
1402-1894
24 boxes, 525 files
Chetham's Library
F.3.1-11
Agecroft
Langleys of Agecroft and Daunteseys of Agecroft
The collection comprises of title deeds and miscellaneous documents relating to Agecroft Hall, which was located in Agecroft, Pendlebury near Manchester, and the Dauntesey and Langley families who owned the Hall.
At a meeting of the Lancashire and Cheshire Antiquarian Society dated 10 Apr 1886, J. P. Earwaker read a paper concerning his work on the Agecroft deeds and charters. The report on this meeting states "These deeds when placed in Mr Earwaker's hands were in a state of great confusion. They were unindorsed, and were lying loose in boxes without order or arrangement. They have now been classified in chronological order, and endorsed. Altogether there are 450 documents, and they have been arranged in twelve sections". The sections, or series, used by Earwaker are detailed in his article for the Transactions of the Lancashire and Cheshire Antiquarian Society.
Based on Earwaker's arrangement but not duplicating it, the Archivist has created 13 series in this catalogue. Although some changes have been made to Earwaker's arrangement, the physical order of the collection has not been altered. A number of documents not catalogued by Earwaker appear in this list. The reference numbers written on the documents have not been altered, and still follow the bundle and deed number order assigned to the documents by Earwaker and earlier cataloguers.
A number of documents catalogued by J. P. Earwaker are not held by Chetham's Library. Please consult the Archivist for more information.
There are no restrictions on access to this collection. Viewing is by prior appointment. Please contact archivist@chethams.org.uk.
J. P. Earwaker, 'An Account of the Charters, Deeds, and Other Documents, Now Preserved at Agecroft Hall, co Lancashire',Transactions of the Lancashire and Cheshire Antiquarian Society, volume IV (1886), pp. 199-220.
The Victoria History of the Counties of England, volume iv, pp. 397 et seq.
The original owners of the manor of Pendlebury were succeeded by the Prestwiches, who owned the adjacent manor of Prestwich. Joan, the daughter of Jordan de Tetlow and his wife Alice, daughter and heiress of Adam de Pretwich, married Richard de Longley c 1360, thereby bringing the manors of Pendlebury, Prestwich and Alkrington together. The Longleys or Langleys were an important local family throughout the fourteenth, fifteenth and sixteenth centuries. When Sir Robert Langley died in 1561 his estates were divided between his four daughters. He left Agecroft and the adjacent lands to his daughter Anne, who married William Dauntesey. The Dauntesey family held the estate into the 20th century.
Agecroft Hall was probably built around the end of the reign of Henry VII, or the beginning of that of Henry VIII. By the end of the 19th century the Hall had fallen into disrepair, and in 1925 it was sold at auction to Thomas C Williams Jr and transported to Richmond, Virginia. It is now an educational trust cared for by the Agecroft Association.
J. P. Earwaker listed the Agecroft charters and deeds in 1885, when they were preserved at Agecroft Hall. When the Hall was sold these documents were removed and deposited in a Manchester bank. They were subsequently deposited in Chetham's Library. However, in 1955-56 a considerable number of documents were removed from Chetham's Library by members of the Dauntesey family. In 1977 the family presented a representative selection of 28 deeds to the new Agecroft Hall in America. In addition, the Agecroft Association have recently purchased a number of documents. Their address is The Agecroft Association, 4305 Sulgrave Road, Richmond, Virginia 23221.
Estate management; Title deeds; Leases (documents); Land tenure -- England; Local history; Langley family. of Prestwich, Pendlebury and Agecroft; Dauntesey family. of Agecroft; Agecroft -- Lancashire -- England; Pendlebury -- Lancashire -- England; Prestwich -- Lancashire -- England; Pendleton -- Lancashire -- England; Salford -- Lancashire -- England; Manchester -- Lancashire -- England; Lancashire -- England
Transactions of the Lancashire and Cheshire Antiquarian Society
The Victoria History of the Counties of England
- Documents relating to the Langleys of Agecroft, 1412-1550; 41 files; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Agecroft/1
  The manor of Prestwich was sold before 1300 to Adam de Prestwich. Richard de Longley married Joan, granddaughter and heiress of Adam de Prestwich. Their son, Roger de Longley, succeeded to the manors of Prestwich, Pendlebury and Alkrington, and the advowson of Prestwich Church. The manors and advowson remained the property of Roger's descendants until the middle of the sixteenth century.
  The Radcliffe family and the Holland family both contested the rights of the Langleys, and disputes were not settled until at least 1376.
  - Marriage Settlement between John de Asshton and Robert de Longley, 20 Jul 1412; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 2 no 60; GB/418/Agecroft/1/1
    For the marriage of Thomas, son and heir apparent of the said Robert, to be married to Margaret, daughter of the said John
    13 Hen IV
  - Grant of the Manor of Tetlow and premises in Oldham, 22 Jul 1412; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 2 no 61; GB/418/Agecroft/1/2
    From Robert de Longley to son his Thomas de Longley and Margaret, daughter of John de Assheton
  - Duplicate Grant of the Manor of Tetlow and premises in Oldham, 22 Jul 1412; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 2 no 63; GB/418/Agecroft/1/3
    From Robert de Longley to his son Thomas de Longley and Margaret, daughter of John de Assheton
  - Attornment of Edmund de Prestwich and Margaret his wife to Thomas de Longley and Margaret his wife for the Manor of Tetlaw, 25 Apr 1413; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 2 no 64; GB/418/Agecroft/1/4
    1 Hen V
  - Receipt from Robert de Longley to John de Assheton and others for 20 marks, 25 Jul 1413; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 2 no 65; GB/418/Agecroft/1/5
  - Inspeximus of the record of a trial at Lancaster, between John, Duke of Lancaster, and Robert de Holland, relating to the Manor of Prestwich etc, 20 Jan 1414; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 2 no 66; GB/418/Agecroft/1/6
    20 Jan 1413/14, 1 Hen V
    Large seal fragment
  - Receipt from Robert de Longley to John de Assheton, 20 Jul 1414; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 67; GB/418/Agecroft/1/7
    2 Hen V
  - Writ from the King, commanding certain persons to answer for having deceived Robert de Longley, 20 Aug 1414; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 68; GB/418/Agecroft/1/8
  - Deed between Robert de Longley and Peres de Holland for the delivery of all deeds etc relating to the manors of Prestwich and Alkrington, 1416; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 69; GB/418/Agecroft/1/9
    3 Hen V
  - Grant of lands called Le Wetepark de Achecroft in the vill of Pendlebury, 1416; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 70; GB/418/Agecroft/1/10
    From Robert de Longley to Peres de Holland for his life
    Monday in the 5th week of Lent, 4 Hen V
  - Lease of lands called Le Wetepark de Achecroft in the vill of Pendlebury, 1416; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 71; GB/418/Agecroft/1/11
    From Peres de Holland to Robert de Longley
    Term: 80 years
    Monday in the 6th week of Lent, 4 Hen V
  - Quitclaim of all right in the manors of Prestwich, Alkrington and Pendlebury, 20 Mar 1416; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 72; GB/418/Agecroft/1/12
    From Thurstan, son of John of Prestwich, to Robert de Longley
    20 Mar 1415/6, 3 Hen V
  - Grant of the manors of Prestwich and Alkrington, 10 Mar 1418; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 73; GB/418/Agecroft/1/13
    From Peter de Holland to John de Workesley
    10 Mar 1417/8, 5 Hen V
  - Grant of messuages, lands etc in Prestwich, 16 Aug 1419; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 74; GB/418/Agecroft/1/14
    From Robert de Longley to Thomas de Longley
    7 Hen V
  - Bond concerning the mortuaries etc of Tottington and Tottington Frith, 24 Jun 1427; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 75; GB/418/Agecroft/1/15
    From Thomas de Hulton to Thurstan de Longeley
  - Exchange of lands in Prestwich, Alkrington and Oldham, 10 Dec 1427; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 76; GB/418/Agecroft/1/16
    Between Robert de Longley and Thomas de Longley and wife Margaret
    6 Hen VI
  - Duplicate exchange of lands in Prestwich, Alkrington and Oldham, 10 Dec 1427; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 77; GB/418/Agecroft/1/17
  - Lease of land in Pendleton, 20 Feb 1453; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 78; GB/418/Agecroft/1/18
    From King to James Longley
    Term: 12 years
    20 Feb 1452/3, 31 Hen VI
  - Testimony of witnesses as to statements made by Thomas, son of Alex Radcliffe of Ordsall, in dispute with Thomas Longley, 12 Mar 1468; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 79; GB/418/Agecroft/1/19
    12 Mar 1467/8, 8 Edw IV
  - Writ from King Edward IV to hold an inquisition after the death of Thomas Langley, 8 Feb 1472; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 80; GB/418/Agecroft/1/20
    8 Feb 1471/2, 11 Edw IV
  - Inquisition taken after the death of Thomas Langley, nd [?1470s]; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 81; GB/418/Agecroft/1/21
    See Agecroft/1/20.
  - Grant of John Longley's lands in co Lancs, 6 Nov 1475; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 82; GB/418/Agecroft/1/22
    From John Longley, esq, to Ralph Longley, clerk, Warden of the Collegiate Church
    15 Edw IV
  - Testimony of witnesses that "Le ffoyecastell more" belonged to the lordship of Prestwich and to the Langleys and not to the manor of Crumpsall, 18 Aug 1479; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 83; GB/418/Agecroft/1/23
    19 Edw IV
  - Declaration of evidence on behalf of John Langley and Robert his son, 30 Sep 1481; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 84; GB/418/Agecroft/1/24
  - Agreement between John Langley and Richard Tong to appear and plead to an action concerning messuages etc in Alkrington, 15 May 1482; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 85; GB/418/Agecroft/1/25
    22 Edw IV
  - Bond in 200 marks from John Radcliffe to John Langley, 12 Jun 1484; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 86; GB/418/Agecroft/1/26
    1 Ric III
  - Award by Thomas, Lord Stanley, between John Radcliffe and John Langley, 15 Jun 1484; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 87; GB/418/Agecroft/1/27
  - Pardon granted to Robert Langley, late of Agecroft, by King Henry VII, 26 May 1486; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 3 no 88; GB/418/Agecroft/1/28
    1 Hen VII
    With fragment of large seal
  - Will of Robert Langley, 24 Feb 1522; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 5 no 104; GB/418/Agecroft/1/29
    24 Feb 1521/2
    Paper
  - Assignment of certain lands in dower, 6 Mar 1528; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 5 no 105; GB/418/Agecroft/1/30
    From Sir Alexander Radcliffe, kt, and others to Eleanor late wife of Robert Langley
    6 Mar 1527/8, 19 Hen VIII
  - Bond in £200 from Robert Holt and Adam Belfeld to Robert Langley, 12 Dec 1533; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 5 no 106; GB/418/Agecroft/1/31
    25 Hen VIII
  - Bond in £40 from Alexander [Brerel] and others to Robert Longley, 6 Jun 1536; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 5 no 108; GB/418/Agecroft/1/32
    28 Hen VIII
  - Lease of the site of the Cell of Kersall, 3 Feb 1539; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 5 no 109; GB/418/Agecroft/1/33
    From Henry VIII to John Wood
    3 Feb 1538/9, 30 Hen VIII
  - Grant of the lease of the Cell of Kersal, 12 Feb 1539; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 5 no 110; GB/418/Agecroft/1/34
    From John Wood to Robert Langley
    12 Feb 1538/9, 30 Hen VIII
    Seal damaged
  - Lease of land in Pendleton, 22 Feb 1539; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 5 no 111; GB/418/Agecroft/1/35
    From King Henry VII to Robert Longley
    Term: 31 years
    22 Feb 1538/9, 30 Hen VIII
  - Receipt from Sir Alexander Radclyff, kt, to Robert Longley for rent due to the King, 21 Oct 1539; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 5 no 112; GB/418/Agecroft/1/36
    31 Hen VIII
  - Receipt from Sir Alexander Radclyff, deputy bailiff to the King for the Wapentake of Salford, to Robert Longley, esq, for certain chief rents, 20 Oct 1540; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 5 no 114; GB/418/Agecroft/1/37
    32 Hen VIII
  - Receipt from Bawdwyn Wylloughby to Robert Langley, 1 Apr 1541; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 5 no 115; GB/418/Agecroft/1/38
  - Receipt from Sir John Williams, kt, Treasurer of the Augmentations of the Revenues of the King, to Robert Langley for £42, 28 Apr 1545; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 5 no 116; GB/418/Agecroft/1/39
    37 Hen VIII
  - Letters patent conveying lands in Pendleton and Salford, 20 May 1545; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 5 no 117; GB/418/Agecroft/1/40
    From King Henry VIII to Robert Langley
    Large seal
  - Articles of agreement between Sir Robert Langley and Thomas Holland concerning an exchange of lands, 19 Jun 1550; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 5 no 118; GB/418/Agecroft/1/41
    4 Ed VI
- Documents relating to the Daunteseys of London and county Wiltshire, 1492-c 1630; 33 files; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Agecroft/2
  William Dauntesey married Anne Langley in 1561. He was the only member of the Dauntesey family to settle in Lancashire.
  - Lease of a burgage etc in Devizes co Wilts, 24 Jun 1492; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 280; GB/418/Agecroft/2/1
    From John Raynold, late of Devizes, brother and heir of Alice Toghyll, late the relict of Thomas Coventry, to Anthony Styleman, gent
    Term: 6 years
    Feast of the Nativity of St John the Baptist, Hen VII
  - Quitclaim of all John Raynold's right in a burgage etc in Devizes co Wilts, 15 Oct 1494; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 281; GB/418/Agecroft/2/2
    From John Raynold brother and heir of Alice Toghyll of Hungerford, late the relict of Thomas Coventry, to Anthony Styleman, gent, and his heirs for ever
    10 Hen VII
  - Grant of the wardship of Richard Dauntesey son and heir of John Dauntesey, dec and kinsman and heir of John Blake, dec, 28 Nov 1506; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 283; GB/418/Agecroft/2/3
    From King Henry VII to Philip Baynard
    Fragment of great seal
    22 Hen VII
  - Grant of a messuage etc in Le Vize co Wilts, 13 May 1532; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 285; GB/418/Agecroft/2/4
    From Anthony Styleman of Steple Assheton co Wilts, gent, to William Dauntesey Citizen and Mercer of London, Ambrose Dauntesey, gent brother of the said William and others, to the use of the said William Dauntesey and his heirs for ever.
    24 Hen VIII
  - Quitclaim of all Anthony Styleman's right in a messuage etc in Le Vize co Wilts, 20 May 1532; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 286; GB/418/Agecroft/2/5
    From Anthony Styleman of Steple Assheton co Wilts, gent, to William Dauntesey, citizen and mercer of London
  - Assignment of a certain yearly payment of £14, payable to Richard Dauncy by Thomas Johns of Harcolston in the Lordship of Haverford West in South Wales, esq, 30 Jul 1538; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 287; GB/418/Agecroft/2/6
    From Richard Dauncy of the House of our Sovereign Lord the King, gent, to William Dauntesey, citizen and alderman of London
    30 Hen VIII
  - Settlement by William Dauntesey citizen and alderman of London, of the reversion of lands etc in Segre and Le Vyes co Wilts and in Stratford at Bow and Bromley, 6 Apr 1539; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 288; GB/418/Agecroft/2/7
    Duplicate at Agecroft/2/8 & Agecroft/2/9
  - Duplicate Settlement by William Dauntesey citizen and alderman of London, of the reversion of lands etc in Segre and Le Vyes co Wilts and in Stratford at Bow and Bromley, 6 Apr 1539; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 289; GB/418/Agecroft/2/8
    Duplicate of Agecroft/2/7
  - Duplicate Settlement by William Dauntesey Citizen and Alderman of London, of the reversion of lands etc in Segre and Le Vyes co Wilts, and in Stratford at Bow and Bromley, 6 Apr 1539; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 290; GB/418/Agecroft/2/9
  - Deed of attornment confirming lands in Segre and Le Vyes co Wilts, and in Stratford at Bow and Bromley, 7 Apr 1539; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 291, 292 & 293; GB/418/Agecroft/2/10
    From Michael Dormer and William Willington to Richard Dauntesey, senior
    Box 1 bdl 1 no 291, 292 & 293 are identical documents
  - Appointment by Michael Dormer and William Willington of Robert Helier and George Findern as their attorneys to receive seisin from William Dauntesey, of messuages, lands etc in the Counties of Derby, Somerset and Wilts, 7 Apr 1539; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 294; GB/418/Agecroft/2/11
  - Agreement made prior to the marriage of Richard Daunsey, esq, and Mary Wolrich, widow, late wife of John Wolrich late of Dudmaston co Salop, esq, decd, and sister to William Gatacre, gent, 10 Dec 1540; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 295; GB/418/Agecroft/2/12
  - Agreement between William Daunsey [Dauntesey,]citizen and alderman of London, and Richard Daunsey, esq, concerning the marriage of the said Richard Daunsey, 16 Dec 1540; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 296; GB/418/Agecroft/2/13
  - Assignment of the office of Receiver of the Queen's Honors, Castles, Lordships etc in the counties of Somerset and Dorset, 31 May 1541; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 297; GB/418/Agecroft/2/14
    And the office of Steward of the Queen's Lordships of Cosham co Wilts, Bridgewater, Holygrove etc, from Richard Daunsey [Dauntesey], Gentleman Usher of the Chamber of the Queen's Grace, to Thomas Mompesson of Corton co Wilts, gent
    33 Hen VIII
  - Letters Patent of messuages etc in London, 20 Jul 1542; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 299; GB/418/Agecroft/2/15
    From King Henry VIII to Richard Dauntesey, esq, and Marie, his wife, for their lives.
    Fragment of great seal.
    34 Hen VIII
  - Assignment, 5 Jun 1543; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 300; GB/418/Agecroft/2/16
    From George Pierpounte of Holme co Notts, esq, to Richard Dauntesey ("Daunce"), esq, servant to 'My Lady Marye is grace', of all his right in a tenement etc lying within the precincts of the late Charterhouse near London
    35 Hen VIII
  - Lease of the sum of 500 marks etc, 21 Jun 1543; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 301; GB/418/Agecroft/2/17
    From Sir Michael Dormer, Knight of the City of London, William Wyllyngton of Barcheston, esq, and Ambrose Dauntesey of Lavington co Wilts, esq, (Executors named in the will of William Dauntesey, Alderman of London, late decd) to Richard Dauntesey, esq, nephew of the said William Dauntesey, decd, and servant to King Henry VIII.
  - Assignment of a lease of the Manor of Denmor co Hereford, and premises in Willington, 17 Jan 1544; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 302; GB/418/Agecroft/2/18
    From Richard Dauntesey of Dudmaston co Salop, esq, to Edward Wolriche of Quatt co Salop, gent
    Term: 19 years
    17 Jan 1543/4, 35 Hen VIII
  - Assignment of a lease of a pasture called Kepronall lying on Dynmore Hill co Hereford, 1 Feb 1548; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 1 bdl 1 no 303; GB/418/Agecroft/2/19
    From Richard Dawntissey (Dauntesey) of Dudmaston co Salop, esq, to John Goodman and William Sympson of Hoope under Dynmore co Hereford
    Term: 15 years
    1 Feb 1547/8, 2 Edw VI
  - Assignment of a lease of a pasture called Kroweshyll lying on Dynmore Hill, co Hereford, 1 Feb 1548; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 2 bdl 2 no 304; GB/418/Agecroft/2/20
    From Richard Dauntysey (Dauntesey) of Dudmaston, co Salop, to Thomas Lawrance and John Robertes of the parish of Chelmars, co Salop
    2 Edw VI
  - Grant in trust of the Manors of Stockham and Norton co Chester, 30 Jun 1548; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 2 bdl 2 no 305 & 306; GB/418/Agecroft/2/21
    From Richard Brooke, esq, to Sir Miles Partrick, kt and Richard Dauntesey, esq
    Box 2 bdl 2 no 305 & 306 are duplicates
  - Lease of a pasture called the Nether end of the Wysteys, 20 Oct 1549; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 2 bdl 2 no 307; GB/418/Agecroft/2/22
    From Richard Dauntesey ("Daunsye") of Dudmaston, co Salop, to William Clarke of Withyngton
    3 Edw VI
  - Release of all actions etc, 12 May 1552; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 2 bdl 2 no 308; GB/418/Agecroft/2/23
    From Thomas Mompesson of Corton co Wilts, gent, to Richard Dauntesey, gent
    6 Edw VI
  - Indenture of apprenticeship of Francis Dauntesey, son of Richard Dauntesey, esq, to Roger Myners, citizen and clothworker of London and Joan his wife [shepster], 25 Jul 1552; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 2 bdl 2 no 309; GB/418/Agecroft/2/24
    Feast of St James the Apostle 6 Edw VI
  - Release for the sum of £80 to the use of Edmund Wolrich and Francis Wolrich, younger sons of John Wolrich late of Dudmaston, esq, and Mary his late wife, now decd, 28 May 1556; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 2 bdl 2 no 310; GB/418/Agecroft/2/25
    From Sir Thomas Gyfford, kt, and William Gatacre, esq, to Richard Dauntesey of Dudmaston co Salop, esq
    2 & 3 Ph and Mary
  - Letter of Attorney concerning premises in the parish of Westham co Essex, 10 Jul 1558; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 2 bdl 2 no 311; GB/418/Agecroft/2/26
    From Richard Dauntesey one of the gentlemen ushers of the Queen's Chamber, to Richard Starky, gentleman waiter of the said chamber
    2 & 4 Ph & Mary
  - Grant of an annuity, 3 Oct 1558; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 2 bdl 2 no 312; GB/418/Agecroft/2/27
    From King Philip and Queen Mary to Christopher Smythe, gent, of an annuity of 20 marks out of the land etc late of Richard Dauntesey, esq, decd, in London, and in the counties of Essex and Wilts during the minority of William Dauntesey, son and heir of the said Richard; and also of the wardship of the said William.
    5 & 6 Ph & Mary
    Great seal - almost intact.
  - Grant of Livery to William Dauntesey of lands in London, Wilts and Essex, formerly belonging to Richard Dauntesey, esq, decd, Feb 1564; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 2 bdl 2 no 313; GB/418/Agecroft/2/28
    Last day of Feb 6 Eliz I
  - Lease for a month of premises in the Counties of Wiltshire, Somerset and Gloucester, 28 Nov 1627; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 2 bdl 2 no 314; GB/418/Agecroft/2/29
    From Sir John Dauntesey of Lavington Bishop, co Wilts, kt, to Robert Newman of Lavington aforesaid, yeo.
    3 Chas
    Mottled due to mould.
  - Settlement by the said Sir John Dauntesey of his manors, messuages, lands etc in the counties of Wiltshire, Somerset and Gloucester, 29 Nov 1627; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 2 bdl 2 no 315; GB/418/Agecroft/2/30
    Between Sir John Dauntesey of Lavington Bishop, co Wilts, kt, Sir John Ernele kt, Sir George Winter kt, Sir John Lambe kt, William Dauntesey of Agecroft, co Lancs esq and others.
    3 Chas I
    Mottled due to mould
  - Assigment in trust of the Manor Prebend etc of Lavington Bishop, and lands in Potterne co Wilts, 29 Nov 1627; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 2 bdl 2 no 316; GB/418/Agecroft/2/31
    From Sir John Dauntesey of Lavington Bishop co Wilts, kt, to Sir John Ernele, kt, Sir George Winter, kt, Sir John Lamb,e kt, and others.
  - Copy of the will of Sir John Dauntesey of Lavington Bishop (epi) co Wilts, kt, 8 Jun 1629; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 2 bdl 2 no 317; GB/418/Agecroft/2/32
    With codicil dated 28 Dec 1630
  - Memorandum relating to the manor of Dale, c 1630; Chetham's Library; GB/418/Box 2 bdl 2 no 318; GB/418/Agecroft/2/33
    Manor of Dale was settled by Sir John Dauntesey, kt, on his daughter Elizabeth on her marriage to Sir John Danvers, for her life.